<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached at the assizes held at Chester, September XX. 1681 by N. Stratford ...</title>
            <author>Stratford, Nicholas, 1633-1707.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1681</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 44 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A61811</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S5939</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R33811</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13567623</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13567623</idno>
            <idno type="VID">100328</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A61811)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 100328)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1050:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached at the assizes held at Chester, September XX. 1681 by N. Stratford ...</title>
                  <author>Stratford, Nicholas, 1633-1707.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 35 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by A.G. and J.P. for Robert Littlebury ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London:</pubPlace>
                  <date>1681.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Acts XXIV, 25 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:100328:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:100328:1"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached at the ASSIZES HELD AT CHESTER, <hi>September</hi> XX. 1681.</p>
            <p>By <hi>N. STRATFORD,</hi> D. D. and Dean of St. ASAPH.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>A. G.</hi> and <hi>J. P.</hi> for <hi>Robert Littlebury,</hi> at the <hi>Kings-Arms</hi> in <hi>Little-Britain,</hi> 1681.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:100328:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:100328:2"/>
            <head>TO THE Right Reverend Father in God JOHN, Lord Biſhop of CHESTER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MY LORD,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ome will perhaps think it a piece of Vanity, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fix ſo great a Name to ſo ſmall a Thing; but how mean ſoever the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing Diſcourſe may be, ſince it is Your Pleaſure it ſhould be ſent to the Preſs, it may juſtly take Sanctuary in Your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip's Patronage: For what more reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, than that He ſhould anſwer for its manifold Defects, who caus'd them to be expos'd to public Cenſure? I thought indeed, that I could not, without ſome appearance of Rudeneſs, reſiſt the impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity of the Honourable Juſtices of
<pb facs="tcp:100328:3"/> Aſſize, and other Perſons of Quality, who heard it preach'd; yet I could not prevail with my ſelf to publiſh it, 'till, to their Deſires, Your Lordſhip added Your Command; and then I thought it my Duty no longer to Diſpute, but forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with to Obey. That it may be ſucceſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful in promoting thoſe important Ends at which it aims, I humbly beg Your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip's Bleſſing and Prayers for it.</p>
            <p>And as this Church is already bleſs'd in Your Lordſhip's moſt Pious and Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Labours; ſo that God would be far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Gracious to it, in giving Your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip Health and long Life to perfect thoſe other great Works You have begun, and to add many more to them, ſhall be the conſtant Prayer of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Lordſhip's moſt humble and moſt obedient Servant, N. STRATFORD.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:100328:3"/>
            <head>A SERMON Preached at the ASSIZES HELD AT CHESTER.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>ACTS 24. 25.</bibl>
                  <p>And as he reaſon'd of Righteouſneſs, Temperance, and Judgment to come, Felix trembled.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>WHich words giving us a brief account of a Sermon prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched by St. <hi>Paul,</hi> concerning the Faith in Chriſt, to <hi>Felix</hi> the <hi>Roman</hi> Governour of <hi>Judea;</hi> in them we
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:100328:4"/> may obſerve, 1. The manner of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle's preaching, <hi>He reaſoned.</hi> 2. Thoſe points of the Chriſtian Faith about which he reaſoned; <hi>Righteouſneſs, Temperance, and Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to come.</hi> 3. The Effect wrought upon <hi>Felix,</hi> by his reaſoning upon theſe; <hi>He trembled.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1. The manner of St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s preaching, <hi>he reaſoned:</hi> As he did not entertain his Hearers with words and noiſe only, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of ſenſe; ſo neither did he Magiſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rially impoſe: But whatſoever he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended, either to their Faith or Practice; as he deliver'd it in a plain, unaffected dreſs of Words; ſo he back't it with ſuch ſtrength of Argument, as was ſufficient not only to Court, but even to Command their aſſent. He knew 'twas in vain to attaque the Will and Affections, before the Underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding was ſubdu'd to the Faith; that while Men follow the conduct of a blind or erring Guide, 'tis not likely they ſhould be reduced from their Wanderings; that no Man can be perſuaded to abandon his Favourite Sin, till he be indeed convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, that 'twill be an evil and a bitter
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:100328:4"/> thing, to hold any longer fellowſhip with it.</p>
            <p>That therefore he might effectually tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlate Men, from the <hi>Power of Satan, to the Kingdom of God;</hi> he firſt endeavour'd to open their Eyes, and to turn them from Darkneſs to Light; to convince them, both of Sin and of Duty, by ſolid uncontrol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lable Arguments; and to give them the moſt forcible Diſſuaſives from the one, the moſt quickening Incentives to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>This was the way of preaching, that in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s judgment was the moſt power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, and therefore the method he here uſed, in order to the Converſion of <hi>Felix.</hi> I therefore humbly crave leave in imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our Apoſtle, briefly to <hi>reaſon</hi> with you, concerning <hi>Righteouſneſs, Temperance, and Judgment to come;</hi> by ſhewing what indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpenſable Obligations we are under, what potent Motives we have, as to the practice of the two former, ſo to the belief of the later. And firſt for <hi>Righteouſneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As the word is not here to be extended to our immediate duty to God, ſo neither ſhall
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:100328:5"/> I confine it to that ſcantling of Juſtice, which relates to another's Eſtate only; but ſhall take it in a middle Latitude, as compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſive of all the duty we owe to our Neighbour, whether with reſpect to his outward, or inward Man: Which tho it be of vaſt extent, yet 'tis uſually reduced to two general Heads; the one Negative, to do him no manner of wrong; either in his Perſon, or in his Relatives, or in his Eſtate, or in any other Capacity: The other Poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, to render him his due; whether it be that which we owe to all Men indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently, (as all common Offices of Huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity,) or to ſome in ſpecial, by virtue of that particular Relation in which we ſtand to them (as <hi>Tribute to whom Tribute is due, Cuſtom to whom Cuſtom, Fear to whom Fear, Honour to whom Honour:</hi>) And not only what is due by the Laws of Men (which are contracted to a narrow compaſs,) but by the more extenſive Law of God. For the Apoſtle here reaſon'd of <hi>Righteouſneſs,</hi> as 'tis a part of the faith of Chriſt, who hath raiſed our Juſtice as high as Charity, and made it our bounden Duty, not only
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:100328:5"/> to do no Evil, but as we have opportunity to do Good to all Men; to feed the Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry, and cloath the Naked; to give Eyes to the Blind, and Feet to the Lame. And that not meerly out of private Deſigns, and ſordid Motives; but from a ſuitable affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and inclination of Will; which is that alone by which all our outward acts of Righteouſneſs are animated, and render'd genuine and acceptable to God.</p>
            <p>This being the Sum of the <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> here meant, how eaſie a matter is it to <hi>reaſon</hi> about it? To demonſtrate, that it is not only highly becoming us, but our neceſſary Duty; and that, both as we are Men, and as we are Chriſtians. For firſt, this is no more, than <hi>to do as we would be done to;</hi> a Law which Nature it ſelf teaches us. Were it a Duty far from us; were we to aſcend to Heaven, to bring it down from above; or to deſcend into the Deep, to fetch it up from beneath; were we to toil and perplex our Brains, either in lofty, or profound enquiries, to find it out; we might then perhaps be excuſed in our neglect of it: But when it is not only nigh us, but within
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:100328:6"/> us, that we need look no farther than our own Breaſts to find our obligation to it; what Apology can we make for our ſelves, in caſe we be found Tranſgreſſors?</p>
            <p>'Tis true, (<hi>Whatſoever ye would that Men ſhould do to you, do ye even ſo to them</hi>) we find among the injunctions of our Bleſſed Saviour; not for that it was not a Law of a more ancient date, but either becauſe it was ſomewhat ſullied by the long growing wickedneſs of the World; or becauſe Men were generally ſo biaſs'd by their corrupt Affections, that they were not willing to take notice of it; he therefore reprinted it in ſo fair a Character, that he that runs may read it: For certain it is, that as it was at firſt impreſs'd upon our Nature, ſo it was never ſo totally defac'd, but that a mere natural Man, by a conſiderate reflexion upon himſelf, might eaſily read it: Witneſs <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtotle, Iſocrates,</hi> and many more,<note place="margin">Diog. Laert. l. 5. in vita Ariſtot. Iſocrat. Orat. ad Demon.</note> conducted only by the light of Reaſon, who own'd themſelves oblig'd to the obſervation of it, before the Laws of Chriſt were publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſh'd to the World. Yea, ſo indelibly is it engraven in our Conſciences, that thoſe
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:100328:6"/> who live in a conſtant defiance to it, are not able to expunge it; for however they tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs it in their dealing with others, yet when their own Rights are concern'd, they always expect, that others ſhould obſerve it toward themſelves. Let us now reflect, and commune a while with our own Hearts.</p>
            <p>Are we willing to be wrong'd our ſelves? Are we content to fall a Sacrifice to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Man's Revenge or Ambition? Do we deſire to be trampled in the Dirt, by thoſe that are greater and ſtronger than we are? Would we be fraudulently circumvented in our Contracts? Would we be blacken'd by falſe defamatory Reports? Would we take it well to have our innocent Words and Actions wreſted to a miſchievous conſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction? In a word; would we have our own Rights in any kind invaded by others? If not, with what face can we aſſault the Body, or undermine the Eſtate, or either openly or ſecretly wound the Reputation of our Neighbour? With what reaſon can we take that Liberty to our ſelves, which we deny to others, who may lay as good
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:100328:7"/> a claim to it as we can? As if we our ſelves only were free from all Duty to others, and all others in Bonds to us. Nor are we more tyed to Juſtice by the Law of our Nature, than we are, 2. By our Intereſt, which, if rightly underſtood, is a Law too.</p>
            <p>'Tis but reaſon that that ſhould moſt ſway us, which, all things conſider'd, is moſt beneficial to us; now would we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trive our own advantage, how can we do it more effectually, than by an exact obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of the Rules of Righteouſneſs? That we are hereby raiſed to a conformity to God himſelf, whoſe Image mainly conſiſts in Righteouſneſs, and true Holineſs; and that by the contrary we degenerate, not only into Beaſts of Prey, but become like the very Devil, who was a Cheater, a Lyar, and a Murderer from the beginning, will, I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, be deny'd by none. And doubtleſs, ſo much the more happy we ſhall be, by how much the more we reſemble the moſt bleſſed Being; ſo much the more miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, by how much the nearer we approach to the moſt accurſed.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:100328:7"/>
            <p>But in caſe we are ſunk ſo far below our Original ſelves, have ſo much forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten our Divine Extraction, as to place our happineſs in the poor, little, ſenſual enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of this World; yet nothing certainly is more highly conducible thereunto, than the exerciſe of Juſtice.</p>
            <p>Were we in the <hi>Leviathan</hi> ſtate of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, in which every Man's hand would be againſt every Man; ſhould one Man blow up our Credits, another ſeize upon our Eſtates, a third make an aſſault upon our Lives; how calamitous and deplorable would our condition be! And yet there is no Man that offers theſe, or any other injury to another, but he thereby provokes and invites another to do the like to himſelf. For what reaſon have we to expect, that others ſhould not mete that meaſure to us, that we have meted to them before?</p>
            <p>'Tis true; we ſhould <hi>do to others,</hi> not as they do, but <hi>as we would</hi> (were we in their circumſtances) <hi>they ſhould do to us:</hi> But the daily practice of the World aſſures us, That the generality of Mankind make our dealing with them the Standard of their
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:100328:8"/> carriage towards us again. And therefore when we injure our Neighbours, we do in effect but wrong our ſelves, becauſe the wrong we do to them, 'tis likely they will return into our own Boſoms: And on the contrary, by every good office we do to others, we engage them to do the like to us; and in caſe they be perſons but of an ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Ingenuity, they will not fail as they have opportunity, to recompenſe us.</p>
            <p>But beſides the obligation this lays upon others, to requite us in the ſame kind; 'tis a thing in it ſelf highly venerable and ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, that makes a Man's face to ſhine, and commends him to the Eſteem of his greateſt Enemies.</p>
            <p>I might alſo ſhew, how <hi>Righteouſneſs exalteth a Nation,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 14. 34.</note> (in the proſperity of which, the welfare of every private perſon is bound up) how Societies are firmly cemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and eſtabliſh'd by it; and by the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, would ſoon be broken into pieces, and ſink into diſſolution.</p>
            <p>But I paſs to a third Conſideration; namely, the near Relation we ſtand in one to another. 'Twas in <hi>Moſes</hi>'s account a
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:100328:8"/> good Argument; <hi>Sirs, ye are Brethren, why do ye wrong one to another?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 7</note> Which alſo the Prophet <hi>Malachi</hi> urged to the ſame purpoſe: <hi>Have we not all one Father? Hath not one God created us? Why then do we deal treacherouſly every Man againſt his Brother?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 2. 10.</note> And St. <hi>Paul</hi> thought us ſufficiently obliged to ſpeak the truth every one to his Neighbour, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>we are Members one of another.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eph. 4. 26.</note> The Learned and the Ignorant, the Rich and the Poor, the Baſe and the Honourable, they are all of the ſame ancient Family, derive their Pedigree from the ſame common Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents. What tho one be a younger, another an elder Brother? Tho one hath a more liberal, another a more ſcant Portion of this World's Goods? Yet ſhould we not ſtill remember that we are Brethren, and be mutually ſerviceable to each other's good?</p>
            <p>Nor are we more cloſely tied together by Nature, than we are by Religion:<note place="margin">Eph. 4. 2, 3, 4.</note> As Chriſtians we are all Members of one Body, are all animated by one Spirit, and call'd in one hope of our Calling. And for thoſe who are ſo many ways one and the ſame,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:100328:9"/> both by Nature and Religion, is it not as monſtrous for them to be injurious one to another, as 'tis for a Man to be cruel to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and to hate his own Fleſh?</p>
            <p>But if theſe Reaſons ſhould be of little force with any Man, there is one Argument ſtill behind, that will undoubtedly be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valent with all thoſe, who are not ſo abſurd, as plainly to contradict their Profeſſion by their Practice.</p>
            <p>For fourthly, What doth the Lord in his written Word more expreſly require, more vehemently inculcate, than to <hi>do juſtly,</hi> and to <hi>love Mercy?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Micah 6. 9. Iſa. 1. 17, 18.</note> Theſe things he accounts, not the Lighter, but the Weightier Matters of his Law,<note place="margin">Mat. 23. 23.</note> and ſets ſo high a value upon them, that he values nothing where theſe are wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting. And tho the <hi>Jews</hi> were generally ſo diſingenuous and ill-natur'd, that God in ſome Caſes, meerly for the hardneſs of their Hearts, made them ſome Allowances; yet he expreſly forbad them, not only to Hurt, but alſo to Hate, or ſo much as bear a Grudge againſt their Brother.<note place="margin">Levit. 19. 17, 18.</note> And can we in reaſon think, that our Bleſſed Saviour, who came not to Evacuate the Law, but to Fulfill it;
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:100328:9"/> who expects, that all his Diſciples ſhould, by their exemplary Virtues, become the Salt of the Earth, and the Lights of the World; and in order thereunto, hath more fully reveal'd our Duty, and <hi>brought Life and Immortality to light,</hi> the more power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully to engage us to the performance of it; can we, I ſay, think, that he made us any Abatements?</p>
            <p>If we will but impartially conſult his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon in the Mount, we ſhall ſoon be reſolv'd in this Matter: We ſhall there find, that he hath laid his Prohibition againſt the Murder of the Tongue, and of the Heart, as well as of the Hand; that rather than knowingly to Do, he hath commanded us patiently to Suffer an Injury; and inſtead of returning <hi>evil for evil,</hi> that on the contrary, we <hi>recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence evil with good.</hi> And becauſe, if there be any perſons in the World that we may be allow'd to do a miſchief to, they may well be ſuppos'd to be thoſe, who, for Chriſt's ſake, are our Enemies, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore His Enemies more than Ours; ſo far is our Saviour from giving us a Licenſe, to do the leaſt Hurt to ſuch as theſe, that he peremp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torily
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:100328:10"/> commands us, to return them all manner of Good, for all manner of Evil: <hi>To bleſs them that curſe us; to do good to them that hate us; and to pray for them, who</hi> (for his ſake) <hi>deſpitefully uſe us, and perſecute us.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 5. 44.</note>
            </p>
            <p>And that he might effectually oblige us to the obſervation of theſe his Laws, he tranſcrib'd them to the Life in his own Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice. As while he lived, he continually went about doing Good to an ungrateful World, and at laſt, freely gave his Life for thoſe who with violent hands took it away; ſo together with his Blood, he alſo pour'd out his Heart, in an ardent Prayer to his Father to forgive them.<note place="margin">Luke 22. 34.</note>
            </p>
            <p>This is the Example we profeſs to follow, and theſe are the Precepts we pretend to obey; yea, which we have ſolemnly vow'd to conform to. And if we are tied by ſuch ſtrong Bonds, to be kind and cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, and good and gracious, and that to thoſe, who (if any Men in the World) deſerve the quite contrary from us; how much more to be juſt and honeſt, that is, as good as Turks and Heathens?</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:100328:10"/>
            <p>I know no greater obligations we can have to any Duty, than theſe already men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned; if we are able to break theſe Bonds, none will be found ſtrong enough to hold us.</p>
            <p>I therefore proceed to the ſecond part of St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Sermon, namely, <hi>Temperance.</hi> This contains our Duty to our ſelves, as the former, that we owe to our Neighbour. The word in the Original<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> denotes Power and Dominion over a Man's ſelf; and tho it may be extended to a due command of all our inordinate Affections and Appetites, of what kind ſoever, yet 'tis here to be limited to the Government of thoſe eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, to the Tyranny of which, <hi>Felix</hi> was moſt enſlav'd; that is, to the Luſts of the Fleſh, as they are diſtinguiſh'd by St. <hi>John,</hi> from <hi>the Luſt of the Eye, and the Pride of Life.</hi> And therefore I ſee no neceſſity of mending our Tranſlation, if we take Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance as comprehenſive both of Sobriety and Chaſtity; as giving Laws to all our exorbitant fleſhly Luſts, and bringing them into ſubjection to the Empire of Reaſon and Religion.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:100328:11"/>
            <p>Now ſo apparently reaſonable is this Duty, that there is no Man ſo bruitiſh, who may not eaſily reaſon himſelf into a ſence of his obligation to it: For whether we conſider our Body, Soul, or Spirit; whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we conſult our Senſe, our Reaſon, or our Religion; we ſhall be furniſhed with ſtore of Arguments to oblige, and of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives to induce us to the practice of it.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Our very Fleſh it ſelf (which alone rebells againſt it) were it capable of reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, would become its Advocate. Tho the ſenſitive Appetite be abſolutely neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to the well being of the Body; yet when it once ſwells too big, and ſtretches beyond thoſe Bounds that Nature hath aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd it, nothing is more deſtructive to the Parent that breeds it; and nothing more highly advantageous, both to the health and pleaſure of the Fleſh, than to retrench the Extravagancies of its own Appetites.</p>
            <p n="1">For, 1. Indulgence to Senſuality is a moſt deadly Enemy to our bodily Health, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which, the Fleſh muſt needs be very ill at eaſe. The Glutton ſwallows a Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe in every intemperate Morſel; and the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:100328:11"/> Wanton fills his Bones with Rottenneſs, as faſt as he empties them of Marrow; and by every ſort of Intemperance, the Senſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſt either begets, or nurſes up ſome Viper, that will prey upon, and devour his beloved Fleſh. 'Twould be endleſs to deſcend to particulars: In general, ſuch numerous Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of Diſeaſes are raiſed and maintained by this Vice alone, as are able to overthrow the ſtrongeſt Conſtitution in the World. And therefore <hi>Diogenes</hi> deſervedly laugh'd at thoſe Sots, who took care to be Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>balm'd after they were dead; and in the mean time, did their endeavour to ſtink and rot while they were alive.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Moderation of our fleſhly Appetites; 'tis a great advantage to the Pleaſures of the Fleſh; it gives them a higher and more generous Taſte, and makes them much more Delicious, than otherwiſe they would be: For by reſtraint our Appetites are quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ened, our Perceptions are render'd more clear and brisk; and by how much the keener our Senſes are, by ſo much the more is the Pleaſure heighten'd. Whereas <note place="margin">Prov. 27. 7.</note>
               <hi>the full Soul loatheth the Honey-Comb, to the hungry</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:100328:12"/> 
               <hi>Soul every bitter thing is ſweet;</hi> a Cruſt of dry Bread, and a Sup of cold Water, when ſawc'd with Hunger and Thirſt, are more delicious than the Banquets of <hi>Cleopatra,</hi> to a gorg'd Stomach.</p>
            <p>For when the Appetite is let looſe, 'tis ſoon tired by its own Extravagancy; 'tis cloy'd and glutted by immoderate Enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and then the moſt exquiſite Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainments of Luſt become not only Unſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voury, but Fulſom. So fooliſh and ſottiſh is the Voluptuous; for Pleaſure's ſake he abandons the greater, and purſues the leſs; he forſakes a Fountain of living Water, and runs to a dirty Puddle to quench his Thirſt.</p>
            <p>And if Intemperance be ſo great an Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my to the Body, then certainly much more, In the ſecond place, doth it War againſt the Spirit; to the nature, working, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement of which, nothing in the World can be more directly oppoſite. It darkens the Mind, and enſlaves the Will; it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrones Reaſon, and exalts Paſſion; it ſof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tens, debaſes, and impoveriſhes the Spirit, and renders us wholly unfit for manly Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertakings; it throws down all our Defences,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:100328:12"/> and expoſes us naked to all the Miſchiefs, that a benighted Underſtanding, an ungo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernable Appetite, and unbridled Paſſions can betray us to. <hi>Whoredom and Wine, and new Wine</hi> (ſaith the Prophet) <hi>take away the Heart;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hoſ. 4. 11.</note> and in <hi>Solomon</hi>'s reckoning, a Drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kard is as ſtupid, as one that <hi>lies down on the top of a Maſt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 23. 34, 35.</note> In a word, Intemperance quite ſtifles the Breath of God within us, and transforms us, not only into Beaſts, but into ſomething far worſe.</p>
            <p>In caſe therefore we have any regard to the well-being, either of our Bodies, or of our Souls here in this World; if we would ſhew our ſelves Men, do any thing becoming the Dignity of our Nature, we need no greater Motives to induce us to live ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berly.</p>
            <p n="3">And yet, 3. By the pure Religion, and undefil'd, which we all profeſs, we are more ſtrongly oblig'd <hi>to cleanſe our ſelves from all filthineſs of the Fleſh, as well as of the Spirit;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 7. 1.</note> and that not only by virtue of its Precepts, but of its Promiſes.</p>
            <p>Firſt, By virtue of its Precepts. As our Bleſſed Saviour himſelf choſe ſuch an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſie
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:100328:13"/> condition of Life, and expoſed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to ſuch a painful Death, as were a perfect Contradiction to all ſenſual Gratifications; ſo he requires, that all thoſe who call them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves by his Name, ſhould ſo far tranſcribe the Copy he hath ſet them, as to <hi>make no proviſion for the Fleſh, to fulfill the Luſts thereof:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 13. 14.</note> And therefore he hath not only cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion'd us againſt <hi>Surfeiting and Drunkenneſs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 21. 34.</note> (the groſſer acts of Intemperance) but hath aſſur'd us, that he will own none for his Votaries, who do not <hi>crucifie the Fleſh, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with its Affections and Luſts.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 5. 24.</note> Nor will it ſuffice, if after we have once nail'd them to the Croſs, we let them looſe again, and ſuffer them to recover of their Wounds; but we muſt rack and torture them, even to Death: For we are commanded to <hi>mortifie our Members which are on the Earth; Fornica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Uncleanneſs, Paſſion, evil Concupiſcence, and inordinate Affection.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Coloſ. 3. 5.</note> Yea, be they Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers as dearly beloved, and ſuch as ſeem as neceſſary and advantagious to us as our right Eye, or our right Hand; we muſt without remorſe pluck them out, and cut them off, and caſt them away from us with abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rency.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:100328:13"/>
            <p>Nor are we more ſtrongly oblig'd to this by the Precepts of our Religion, than we are, In the ſecond place, by its <hi>exceeding great and precious Promiſes,</hi> which are given us to this very end, <hi>That by them we may be made partakers of a Divine Nature, having eſcaped the Pollution that is in the World through Luſt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Pet. 1. 4.</note> For as theſe Promiſes are all made to thoſe only, who through the Spirit do mortifie the Deeds of the Body; ſo the good things promiſed are of ſuch a refin'd and ſpiritual Nature, that no others are capable of en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joying them. For put the caſe, that God ſhould lay open the Encloſure, and give free leave to a Senſualiſt to enter into the Regions of immortal Bliſs; yet a perſon of ſuch a bruitiſh Temper, would be as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſpoſed to reliſh the Entertainment there, as a Goat is to taſt the Pleaſures of Muſic. For there is not any thing in Heaven that is ſuitable to the deſires of a carnal Man; there is not ſo much as <hi>eating or drinking;</hi> there is no <hi>marrying, nor giving in Marriage;</hi> much leſs any intemperate Cups, or unclean Embraces, to entertain the Voluptuary with. Such are the Joys above, as mainly conſiſt
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:100328:14"/> in the Viſion of God; and how can he take any pleaſure in God, who can behold no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in him, but what is as oppoſite to his own Inclinations, as Light to Darkneſs? No, the preſence of the infinitely bleſſed Being would fill ſuch a Soul with Confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and Horrour, and make him almoſt as much deprecate the being in Heaven, as in Hell.</p>
            <p>If therefore we have any love to our ſelves; if we deſire to be happy, either in the Life that now is, or in that which is to come; inſtead of pampering our fleſhly Luſts, we ſhall rather ſtarve them, and hold them in as with Bit and Bridle, till they become tame and tractable, and humble Servants to our Souls.</p>
            <p>But if we are ſo far bewitch'd with Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuality, as not to be diſenchanted by ſuch calm and gentle Reaſoning, 'tis high time to proceed to that which is more loud and thundering, namely, <hi>The Judgment to come,</hi> the third and laſt part of the Apoſtle's Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon. That the Doctrine of a Judgment to come is no cunningly devis'd Fable, we may be undoubtedly aſſur'd, (if we can be
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:100328:14"/> ſo of any thing) and that both by Reaſon and Revelation.</p>
            <p>For Firſt, We find it impreſs'd by God himſelf upon our Minds.</p>
            <p>Secondly, It neceſſarily reſults from the natural Notion we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ave of God</p>
            <p>And Thirdly, We are infallibly aſſur'd of it by Divine Revelation.</p>
            <p>Firſt, The Doctrine of a future Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is by God himſelf impreſs'd upon our Minds, and therefore hath been ever own'd, even by thoſe perſons, who had no other Teacher than themſelves. 'Tis needleſs to give a particular account of thoſe Heathen Writers, who have given their Atteſtation to this Article of our Faith: He that will not be at the pains to peruſe the Authors themſelves, may find many of their Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies collected, by St. <hi>Clemens</hi> of <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dria, Juſtin Martyr, Euſebius,</hi> and others.<note place="margin">Clem. Alex. Stromat. l. 5. p. 606. Juſt. Mart. de Monarch. Dei, &amp; Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raen. ad Graec. Euſeb. de Praeparat. Evang. l. 11. c. 38. l. 12. c. 6.</note> And that this Notion derives its Pedigree from God himſelf, who can have no deſign to cheat and abuſe us, will eaſily appear by theſe Conſiderations.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe it is not the product of Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution only; for if it were, how came it
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:100328:15"/> to paſs, that the moſt rude and uninſtructed Nations in the World have been ever poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs'd with it? That the barbarous <hi>Indians,</hi> and the ſalvage <hi>Americans,</hi> had a prenotion of Rewards and Puniſhments in another World, we cannot ſo much as queſtion, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs we will be ſo unreaſonable, as to call in queſtion the Truth of the moſt credible Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtories. Beſides, if the conceit of a Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to come proceeded from hence, there muſt be ſome Man who firſt broach'd it: And by whom was he taught, who firſt taught it to others? And if it took not its Original from Inſtitution, 'twill yet appear more highly credible, that 'tis by the God of Nature interwoven with the very Eſſence of our Souls; in that,</p>
            <p n="2">2. Thoſe perſons are poſſeſs'd with a Fear of this Judgment, who can have no ground of Fear, but what they find in themſelves. Whence is it, that they who commit Villa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies in the Dark; or in the ſolitary Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, without any Witneſs but God and their own Conſciences, cannot reflect upon their Sins without Fear and Regret? They are in no danger of any earthly Tribunal; what
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:100328:15"/> then can they dread but the Judgment of Heaven? Whence is it, that thoſe perſons, whoſe very name is a Terrour to evil doers, in caſe they themſelves do evil, do often become a Terrour to themſelves? Whom do they fear? To whom are they accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table? But to him only who is higher than the Higheſt, who will judge the Great and the Small, the Strong and the Weak, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out reſpect of Perſons.</p>
            <p>Which is yet, In the third place, more ſtrongly concluded; Becauſe many per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, who do their utmoſt to ſtupifie and debauch their Conſciences, are by no means able to rid themſelves of this troubleſome Gueſt; which certainly they would be, were it not connatural to them.</p>
            <p>Many there are who ſet their Mouth againſt Heaven, and their Tongue walketh through the Earth; who ſet themſelves down in the Chair of the Scorner; who droll upon Religion, and make a mock at Sin, and laugh aloud at a Judgment to come, and proclaim them all for Fools or Knaves, who endeavour to poſſeſs Men with a firm, ſteadfaſt, practical Belief of theſe things.
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:100328:16"/> And yet theſe jolly Men cannot get an abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute Conqueſt over their own Conſciences; but maugre all the Violence they offer to them, and the ſtrongeſt Bands of Iniquity they can bind them with, they ſometimes break looſe, and hale them to the Bar, and pronounce that Sentence againſt them here, that ſhall hereafter be pronounc'd by Chriſt himſelf in the General Aſſembly of the whole World.</p>
            <p>From all which it plainly appears, That the Notion of a Judgment to come, is not the product of Superſtition or Credulity, of a feminine Underſtanding, or an abus'd Phancy; but ſo deeply impreſs'd by God himſelf upon our Minds, that nothing is able to eraſe it.</p>
            <p>Secondly, A future Judgment is neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily concluded, from the natural Notion we have of God. That God is a Being abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely perfect, there is no Man but by the exerciſe of his rational Faculties, may ſoon attain to the knowledge of; and by neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary conſequence, that he is neither ignorant, nor impotent, nor unjuſt, nor unmerciful; but ſo infinitely Knowing, that all Sins, how
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:100328:16"/> ſecret ſoever or diſguis'd, are naked and open to his Eyes; ſo Powerful, that the moſt po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent Sinner is not able to ſtay his Hand; ſo Holy, Juſt, and Good, that he cannot but diſcountenance Vice, and encourage Virtue, and will ſome time or other render to every Man according to his Works. All this is no more than what the very Notion of God includes: And yet, where can the Man be found, that is ſo quick ſighted, as to be able to obſerve ſuch a Diſpenſation of Recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pences in this World, as bears any Proportion to this Idea?</p>
            <p>'Tis true indeed, there is no Age, but affords ſome ſuch remarkable Examples of God's Juſtice, as (if duly conſider'd) would give check to the boldeſt Sinners: But theſe are comparatively rare; where one is bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with a mark of Divine Vengeance, how many Hundreds eſcape untouch'd? Accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the common courſe of Providence, <hi>There is one event to the Righteous, and to the Wicked; to the Clean, and to the Unclean.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccl. 9. 1, 2.</note> Yea, do we not ſometimes ſee the Wicked lift up their Horn on high, while the Righteous hang down their Heads? <note place="margin">Eccl. 10. 6, 7.</note>
               <hi>Folly ſet in great</hi>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:100328:17"/> 
               <hi>Dignity, and the Rich ſit in low Place? Servants riding on Horſes, and Princes walking as Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants on the Earth?</hi> The beſt of Kings brought to a Scaffold, and the worſt of Rebels ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanc'd to his Throne? And ſuch unequal Adminiſtration of Affairs, as ſeems ſo ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd and prepoſterous to common Reaſon, can we think it the ultimate reſult of infinite Wiſdom, and Power, and Juſtice? Are we not hence forc'd to conclude, that there ſhall be another day, in which all that is now crooked, ſhall be made ſtrait; and all that is rough, ſhall be made plain? when the Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous ſhall lift up their Heads with joy, and the Wicked (<hi>who now account their Life mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and their End to be without honour</hi>)<note place="margin">Wiſd. 5. 3, 4.</note> ſhall be forc'd with Anguiſh to confeſs; <hi>Verily, there is a Reward for the Righteous; doubtleſs there is a God that judgeth in the Earth.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 58. 11.</note>
            </p>
            <p>But, Thirdly, We have yet a more ſure word of Revelation, which expreſly tells us, That <hi>God hath appointed a day in which he will judge the World in Righteouſneſs:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 17. 31.</note> That <hi>we muſt all appear before the Judgment Seat of Chriſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 5. 10.</note> 
               <hi>that every one may receive the things done in his Body, according to that he hath done, whether it</hi>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:100328:17"/> 
               <hi>be good or bad:</hi> That in order to this, <hi>the Lord himſelf ſhall deſcend from Heaven with a ſhout, with the voice of the Archangel, and the Trumpet of God;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Theſ. 4. 16.</note> That <hi>all that are in the Graves ſhall hear his Voice, and ſhall come forth; they that have done Good, to the Reſurrection of Life; and they that have done Evil, to the Reſurrection of Damnation.</hi>
               <note place="margin">John 5. 27, 28.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Knowing therefore this Terrour of the Lord, let us be perſuaded to <hi>walk honeſtly, as in the day; not in Rioting and Drunkenneſs; not in Chambering and Wantonneſs; not in Strife and Envying; but to put on the Lord Jeſus Chriſt:</hi> That ſo this great Day of the Lord, that will be a day of Fire and Brimſtone, of Storm and Tempeſt, to all ſuch as walk after the Fleſh, may be a day of Jubilees, and of Triumphs to us. And that we may be indeed perſuaded to this, I ſhall briefly repreſent the Terrours and Amaze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, wherewith all unrighteous and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauch'd Perſons will then be ſeiz'd.</p>
            <p>Let us imagine, that we now heard the voice of the Archangel; <hi>Ariſe ye Dead, and come to Judgment:</hi> That we thereupon ſtar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted out of our Graves, and found the whole
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:100328:18"/> Earth on Fire about us, and heard the fearful Thunders, and diſmal Groans, of the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolving World: That we ſaw the Judge upon the Throne of his Glory, attended with Millions of the glittering heavenly Hoſt: That we ſaw vaſt Armies ariſing out of the Sea, and Death and Hell delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring up the Dead that were in them: That the Books were then open'd, and all the hidden things of Darkneſs brought to Light, the moſt ſecret Sins made manifeſt.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi ſe tunc impii vide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunt? <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi adulteri, ubi ebrioſi, ubi maledici ſe recogno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcent? <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi amatores luxuriae, ubi raptores, ubi ſuperbi &amp; invidi apparebunt? Quid infeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces pro ſua defenſione dicturi ſunt, quos totiens admonitos, &amp; tamen imparatos dies ille repererit? Cum ad illam Archangeli tubam omni buccina clariorem, totus ſimul coeperit mugire mundus, &amp;c. Aug. de Tempore, Serm. 54.</note> With what confuſion of face (think you) would the Deceiver, the Hypocrite, appear before the Righteous and All-ſeeing Judge? He that can now put a fair Face upon the fouleſt Matter; that can dreſs up Schiſm and Faction in the Garments of Peace and Unity, and transform Sedition and Rebellion into Loyalty and Obedience; how will he be cover'd with Shame and Bluſhing, when the Mask ſhall be pull'd off, and all that Paint and Daub waſh'd away, by which he Smooth'd, and put a Gloſs upon his moſt
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:100328:18"/> wrinkled and deformed Actions? He that now thinks it a fine thing to over-reach his Brother, that decoys him into an evil Net, and then braves himſelf as a Man of Wit and Parts for ſo doing<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> How will he be at his Wits ends, when too late he ſhall be convinc'd, with a Vengeance, that Honeſty was the beſt Policy, and that he was a wiſe Man, who choſe to part with his own, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than uſurp another Man's Rights? He that is now Mighty to drink Wine, and a Man of Strength to pour down Strong Drink, who leaves Trophies of his Victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries at every drunken Meeting; how will his Courage be cool'd, and his Creſt fall? How will he ſneak into a Den to hide his guilty Head, when all his Rioting and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velling, and Swaggering, and Swearing, and Ribaldry, (for which he was here hugg'd and applauded by his dear Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions) ſhall be expoſed naked, in all their Shame and Turpitude, to the view of all the holy Angels, and of all the good and wiſe Men that ever liv'd? And when after their Sins have been made bare, and held up to the View of all the World, that dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:100328:19"/> Sentence ſhall thunder in their Ears; <hi>Depart from me ye Curſed into everlaſting Fire, prepar'd for the Devil and his Angels:</hi> What inexpreſſible Horrours and Agonies will then poſſeſs them? Methinks I hear their deſpairing Cry. What! is this the end of my fleſhly and worldly Luſts? Is this that for which I have taken ſo much Pains, and ſpent ſo much Time? Have I ſo often reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted the Holy Ghoſt, and offer'd Violence to my own Conſcience, to bring my ſelf to this woful State? Prodigious Sot! had I done and ſuffer'd but half ſo much in morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying my ſinful Luſts, as I did in gratifying them, I had now been crown'd with an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding and eternal weight of Glory. <note place="margin">Magna eſt ejus ſeveri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas poſt Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicium, cujus ante Judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cium ineffa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilis miſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordia pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogata eſt. Aug. de Verb. Dom. in Evang. ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cund. Matth. Serm. 22.</note> But alas! 'tis now too late; the date of Mercy is out, and the day of Vengeance is come; the fatal Sentence is already paſt, that will never be revok'd; the Judge is now inexo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, no Prayers nor Tears, no Sighs nor Groans, will move him to Pity; nothing remains for me but Torments great and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolerable, without End, without Intermiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, without the allay of one Glimpſe of Hope. And <hi>who can dwell with devouring</hi>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:100328:19"/> 
               <hi>Fire? Who can dwell with everlaſting Burnings? Oh! 'tis a fearful thing to fall into the hands of the Living God!</hi> So fearful, that the very pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>apprehenſions of it is enough to make the ſturdieſt Sinner to tremble; which was the effect wrought upon <hi>Felix</hi> by St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoning: The third and laſt thing conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable in the Text.</p>
            <p>That <hi>Felix</hi> was as ſtrongly fortifi'd againſt the Aſſaults of Conſcience as moſt Men in the World, we ſhall have no reaſon to doubt, if we read the Character given of him by <hi>Joſephus</hi> and <hi>Tacitus;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joſeph. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiqu. Jud. l. 20. c. 6. Tacit. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal. 12. 11. Hiſt. 5. 3.</note> and yet being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcious to himſelf of a wicked Life, the Voice of a poor deſpiſed Priſoner citing him to a Judgment to come; ſets him a Trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling.</p>
            <p>By which we plainly ſee, that the Arrows of an evil Conſcience are ſo piercing, that there is no Armour of Proof againſt them; that its Aſſaults and Batteries are ſo ſtrong and violent, that no Bulwark is able to withſtand them: But be the Sinner never ſo Great and Powerful, never ſo Daring and Reſolute; yet <note place="margin">Wiſd. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note>
               <hi>Wickedneſs being condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by its own Witneſs, will be very timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous;</hi>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:100328:20"/> 
               <hi>and being preſs'd with Conſcience, will always forecaſt Grievous Things:</hi> Witneſs the moſt Potent, and the moſt Inſolent Sinners that ever were; ſuch as <hi>Tiberius, Caligula</hi> and <hi>Nero,</hi> in Heathen Story; beſides <hi>Cain, Belſhazzar,</hi> and others, recorded in Holy Scripture.</p>
            <p>What then remains, but that forthwith we reconcile our ſelves to our own Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces? That when they deal faithfully with us, and tell us roundly of our Sins, and of the Judgment to come, for them; we do not rudely ſhuffle them off (as <hi>Felix</hi> did St. <hi>Paul</hi>) to a more convenient Seaſon; that we no longer ſtifle our Convictions, and check our Tremblings, but ſuffer them to proceed to a ſincere Converſion; not only to the ſhaking of our vicious Habits, but to the tearing them all up by the Roots, and utterly deſtroying them; that whatſoever we have done amiſs heretofore, we do ſo no more: But for the future <hi>denying all Ungodli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and worldly Luſts, that we live Soberly, Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſly, and Godly, in this preſent World:</hi> That ſo when we ſhall be Summon'd to appear before the Judge of all the Earth, being firſt
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:100328:20"/> acquitted by our own Conſciences, we may alſo be abſolv'd by the Judge, and may be advanc'd to an <hi>Inheritance incorruptible, and undefil'd, and that fadeth not away, reſerv'd in Heaven for all thoſe, who, by patient continuance in well-doing, do ſeek for Glory, and Honour, and Immortality:</hi> Which God of his infinite Mercy grant, for the Merits of our Bleſſed Saviour; to whom be aſcrib'd, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
